<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful testimony and warning concerning the certainty of the great and notable day of the Lord, broken forth in this age after the long night of apostacy, wherein he will accomplish his great and glorious work, determined, of redemption and restauration : with something concerning the sufficency of the grace of God ... : and a few words in reply to such as query, or ask, Whether did you ever hear or read of a people, in all the Scriptures, that were Quakers ... / by William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13956</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13588463</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13588463</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100607</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 783:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful testimony and warning concerning the certainty of the great and notable day of the Lord, broken forth in this age after the long night of apostacy, wherein he will accomplish his great and glorious work, determined, of redemption and restauration : with something concerning the sufficency of the grace of God ... : and a few words in reply to such as query, or ask, Whether did you ever hear or read of a people, in all the Scriptures, that were Quakers ... / by William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probable place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100607:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100607:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Faithful Teſtimony AND WARNING</p>
            <p>Concerning the Certainty of the Great and Notable Day of the Lord, broken forth (in this Age) after the long Night of Apoſtacy; wherein he will accompliſh his great and glorious Work (determined) of Redemption and Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>With ſomething concerning the <hi>Sufficiency</hi> of the <hi>Grace of God, which hath appeared to all men, &amp;c.</hi> Tit. 2.11. And of the <hi>true Light, which lighteth every man that comes into the World,</hi> Joh. 1. With a brief Exhortation to them that believe in the Light, and are turned from the <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> Satan's power, to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a few words in Reply to ſuch as query, or ask, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did you ever hear or read of a People (in all the Scriptures) that were</hi> Quakers; <hi>and that preached of a Light Within, as you called</hi> Quakers <hi>do? And whether you own the Scriptures to be the Word of God? And whether you do not hold that dangerous Tenet of Perfection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All briefly Anſwered, and given forth, for the ſake of the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſilence the <hi>Fooliſh-ignorant,</hi> and to reprove the <hi>Scorner;</hi> that all ſuch may <hi>Awake, Repent</hi> and <hi>Turn to the Lord,</hi> before it be too late: for it is the Day of their Viſitation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In True Love to all your Souls, by</hi> William. Bayly.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:100607:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100607:2"/>
            <head>A Faithfull Teſtimony AND WARNING, Concerning the Certainty of the Great and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Day of the Lord, broken forth (in this Age) after the Long Night of Apoſtacy; wherein he will accompliſh his Great and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Work (determined) of Redemption and Reſtauration.</head>
            <p>THe Great and Notable Day of the Lord is now dawned, and broken forth, which hath been propheſied of ſince the Beginning, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> tranſgreſſed <hi>[That the Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpent's Head]</hi> And by the Mouthes of his holy Prophets, from <hi>Enoch</hi> to the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who alſo propheſied of this Day, and the Work which therein ſhould be accompliſhed; which was then begun (though hindred by the Apoſtacy) for a time (fore-ſeen) and for an End determined: but now will the Lord God work, and none ſhall hinder; for the ſet time is come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſied of this Day, chap. 2. verſ. 2, 3. And <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> propheſied, chap. 50. And <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 39. And <hi>Daniel</hi> 12. And <hi>Hoſea,</hi> chap. 6.2, 3. And <hi>Joel,</hi> chap. 2. And <hi>Amos,</hi> chap. 8. <hi>Obad.</hi> verſ. 21. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4. <hi>Nahum</hi> 1. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.5. &amp; 2.20. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12, 13, 14, 15, &amp;c. <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Zech.</hi> 6. and chap. 9. verſ. 8, 9, to the end. And <hi>Malachi</hi> 3.1. and 4.1, &amp;c. And <hi>John</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100607:3"/>Baptiſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. And Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. Theſe all propheſied of this Mighty and Glorious Day, wherein God would finiſh Tranſgreſſion, and make an end of Sin, and bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs, and make a new Heaven, and a new Earth (which <hi>John</hi> ſaw) and exalt the Mountain of his own Houſe above all the Hills, and eſtabliſh it a top of all the Mountains, and many People ſhould flow unto it, and flock as Doves to the Windows: and that this Day of the Lord ſhould burn as an Oven, and all the Proud, and all that do Wickedly ſhould be as Stubble, and the Day that [cometh] ſhall burn them up, and leave neither Root nor Branch of the VVicked: and the Day of the Lord [ſhall be] upon every one that is high, and lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low; and the Lord [alone] ſhall be exalted in that Day: and the little Stone (which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw) cut out of the Mountain without hand, that broke the great divided Image to pieces, and filled the whole Earth: and the time wherein [many] ſhould be tryed, and purified, and made white (but the VVicked doing wickedly) and the Knowledge of the Glory of God ſhould cover the Earth, as the VVater cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Sea. This is the VVork which the Eternal God is now doing in this Day of his Power, which is come as a Thief in the Night upon many, who will not believe, though it be declared unto them.</p>
            <p>The Son of Man is come, and coming in the Clouds of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with Power and great Glory; the Tribes (or Kindreds) of the Earth mourning and wailing becauſe of him, who is come in Thouſands of his Saints (or holy Ones) to judge the World, and convince the Ungodly of their ungodly Deeds and hard Speeches; Antichriſt and Son of Perdition revealed, and conſuming by the Spirit of his Mouth, and ſhell be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Brightneſs of his Glory; and the Son of God is come; and theſe are Signs of his coming, and of his Glory, whom the Princes of this World never knew. The Fig-tree hath bloſſomed, and put forth her tender Bud, we know the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is nigh; the Body is known to which the Eagles are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; the two in the Field, the two at the Mill, and in the Bed, are ſeparated; and the Unclean Spirits are tormented,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100607:3"/>and the Devils caſt out, and enter'd into the Herds of Swine, making them run with Violence, till they are choked; who have trampled the Pearls under their Feet, and turned again, and rented, as Chriſt Jeſus (our elder Brother) ſaid they would do; and the Dead are raiſed; the Blind (yea, the born blind) receive their ſight; the Deaf hear; the Dumb ſpeak, with new Tongues, the wonderful things of God; the Lame walk; the Lepers are cleanſed; and the Poor (in Spirit) receive the Goſpel, which is the Power of God to Salvation: Theſe things are now again witneſſed and fulfilled.</p>
            <p>The Great Day of the Lamb's Appearance (the ſecond time to Salvation) is come; the Battle of the Great GOD is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; his Dividing Two-edged Sword is drawn; the Ax is laid to the very Root of the Tree; the Plough of the Almighty is entred into the Earth, and many have ſet their hands to it, (bleſſed be the Lord God forever) and dare not look back again to <hi>Sodom;</hi> and the World is turning up-ſide down; and the Unquenchable Fire is kindled-among the Bryars, and Thorns and Stubble, and it will conſume them.</p>
            <p>Wickedneſs hath made the whole World like as a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and like a Garden all grown over with Thiſtles and Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, wherein the Lord God cannot take delight; but hath been (and is) grieved therewith, and greatly diſhonoured and provoked: Great hath been the time of his Long-ſuffering; long hath his Lilly lain among the Thorns, his tender, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, holy Seed under the Clods of the Earth and Rocks of the Mountains; grievous and long hath been the Oppreſſions and Sufferings of the Lamb of God, ſince the Foundation of the World: But now he is coming up in his Dyed Garments, who hath Troden the VVine-preſs alone; and the Day of Vengeance is in his Heart; and he will trample the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor in his Fury; for the Year of his Redeemed is come.</p>
            <p>And as it was in the dayes of <hi>Lot,</hi> and in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> ſo ſhall be at the coming of the Son of Man, with Power and great Glory; and this is witneſſed: and the Clouds of Heaven hath received him out of the ſight of all the Gazers, and Deſpiſers, and VVonderers that periſh, and the blind <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100607:4"/>that cannot find <hi>Lot</hi>'s Door; for our Door is Chriſt Jeſus, and he is the Truth, and the Way to the Father and Kingdom of God, which none can ſee except a man be born again; and whoever climbs another Way, is a Thief, and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and will be condemned by him, to whom all Judgment is committed, which ſtands at the Door; read within <hi>(for its the fooliſh Woman that is without.)</hi> And a Witneſs hath God placed in every mans Conſcience, according to whoſe Righteous Judgment he will judge the ſecrets of all people: And this is not another then the Univerſal Light of the Son of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Chriſt Jeſus, who is come with his Fan in his hand, and will throughly purge his Floor; and is now ſetting up his true VVorſhip again, after the Night of Apoſtacy, as he ſpoke, <hi>[The Hour is coming, &amp;c.]</hi> this Hour is now come, and the Father is ſeeking true VVorſhippers to worſhip him, in the Spirit, and in the Truth, which was begun Sixteen Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years ago; and theſe onely are the True VVorſhippers, <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Though in the Times of Ignorance God is ſaid to VVink, (the Light cloſed in, or not ſo manifeſted) but now he calls all men every where (who are in Darkneſs, Ignorance and VVickedneſs) to Repent, and turn at his Reproofs, leſt they dye in their ſins, and ſo never come to enjoy the Soul's Reſt, (which is prepared for the Obedient) of which the outward Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both was a Figure, as all the other of the Temple-VVorſhip, and Sacrifices, and Ceremonies, were but Types, Figures and Shadows, and not the heavenly things themſelves, no more then the Shadow of a man, or an Image drawn of him, is the very man himſelf: The Subſtance (or Body) is Chriſt, as it is written, by whom the VVorld was made; though the VVorld knew him not, he was in the VVorld before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, or <hi>Adam</hi> either; the VVord of God, the Truth, the true Bread, the true High-Prieſt, Temple and Tabernacle, the true Prophet, the true VVay, and true Reſt to the Immortal Soul; of which living immortal Subſtance the Lord God expected (and waited) to ſee, if the people would perceive ſomething beyond all theſe Shadows and Figures, which made nothing perfect, as pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100607:4"/>to the Conſcience, but they remaining hardened, and in the Blindneſs of their minds, underſtood not <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, though they had their Writings read every Sabboth day; and ſo not-anſwering the Mind and Will of God, but perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering in Sin and Wickedneſs, and depending on thoſe out-ſide things commanded, and ſettled on their Lets, and Name of Profeſſion; the Lord raiſed up (and ſent his Servants) the Prophets, to try againſt them, both Prieſts, Rulers and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as being weary of the multitude of their Sacrifices and Services, and their Holy Things became Abominable to him; <hi>the ſacrificing a Lamb, as if they cut off a Dog's Neck; and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Incenſe, as if they bleſſed an Idol, and offered Swine's Bleed</hi> (the Life of a <hi>Swine</hi>) this was their ſtate, by reaſon of their groſs Hearts and deaf Ears, which were hardened and ſtopped through the Deceitfulneſs of ſin, in which they continued; ſo that none truly ſeek'd after God, but were all out of the Way of Peace and true Attonement; groſs Darkneſs covered the People; the Ox and Aſs-knew their Owner and Maſter's Crib, better then they knew their Maker, whoſe Love and render Care was towards them, in viſiting them that their ſouls might live; for that was the Cry of his Servants beyond all their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Worſhip. <hi>Turn ye, turn ye; why will ye dye and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in your Iniquities?</hi> for iniquity and ſin was their Ruin, as God fore-warned them of it: For that was the cauſe of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that was kindled againſt them, and of hiding his Face (and with-holding Good Things) from them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſame Partition-Wall at this day, among all blind, hard-hearted, poluted <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> who are rending and tearing about Shadows, and devouring one another about fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding periſhing Things, not minding the Mighty Day of God, that is now come and coming, wherein your Heavens ſhall be on Fire, and Elements melt with fervent heat (for it burns like an Oven) and the old Earth, and its Works muſt be burnt up, Root and Branch: This Work is begun amongſt ye, though the Blind cannot ſee, who have Eyes, and ſee not; and Ears, and hear not, like the old <hi>Jews.</hi> And now thouſands of Rams, and Ten Thouſand of Rivers of Oyl, will do no good, as pertaining
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100607:5"/>to the Conſcience: <hi>Nay, If I ſhould give the Firſt-born of my Body for the Sin of my Soul, it would not be accepted;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> its only the Blood of the Son of God (the Life) as of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lamb without Spot and Blemiſh, that can redeem it out of Tranſgreſſion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile it unto God, who had a Body prepared, in the fulneſs of time, to end all the outward Sacrifices under the Law, through which the New and Living Way was conſecrated through the Vail, that is to ſay, <hi>his Fleſh:</hi> which Vail all blind Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors and Prophane in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> cannot yet ſee through to this day, no more then the blind <hi>Jews</hi> and blind Guides could ſee the end of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets words, to the <hi>Everlaſting Prieſthood, and Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth</hi> (within the Vail) though they had the Scriptures; who cannot ſee to the <hi>Beginning,</hi> beyond the <hi>Viſibles,</hi> to the <hi>only wiſe inviſible God, before Bread, and Water, and Wine, and Books, and Prieſts Lips, that Preach for Money, and Hire and Gain from their Quarter;</hi> which the Prophets ſaw beyond, and cryed againſt; <hi>and them that bore rule by their Means, which was a filthy and horrible thing.</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw Chriſt's Day, before <hi>Moſes</hi> was born. And <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſaw beyond the Water, to the <hi>Fire and Holy Ghoſt's plunging,</hi> to the <hi>Chriſt that was before him</hi> (and to the <hi>Fan in his Hand</hi>) <hi>and preferred before him;</hi> ſaying, <hi>He muſt Increaſe, but I muſt Decreaſe:</hi> Yet <hi>John</hi> was born (outwardly) before him, and his Miniſtry a <hi>Fore-runner, and Signifier of the Day at hand, of through Purging, and fanning the Chaff from the Wheat, by the unquenchable Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear this, ye Profeſſors of Chriſt Jeſus (who feed upon Husks) Can ye believe this Work is now again begun, and that Fire can ſwallow up Water (as in dayes of old) and that the Elements ſhall melt with fervent Heat, as was Propheſied of? and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> decreaſing by degrees, till there is no Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter left to comfort the Soul, but of that ſort the man in Hell Torment wanted, which the true Believer, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> had enough of? as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that believeth in me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his Belly (or inmoſt parts) ſhall flow a River of Living Water, which ſhall be [in] him a Well of Water, ſpringing up unto Eternal Life: And he that eateth my Fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100607:5"/>my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him: and except ye eat my Fleſh, and drink my Blood, ye have no Life in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was not this a hard Saying? and many more he had to ſay to them, which they could not bear then, nor many cannot bear now; though they profeſs the ſame in words, the Life they are ignorant of that gave them forth, which God hath manifeſted to them that waited for his pure ſpiritual Appearance; and the Day is come where in the true Worſhip is ſet up again (as I have ſaid) after the Apoſtacy, the falling away from the true Life, the Power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and from the true Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, as was fore-told by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> 2 2. and ſeen by <hi>John; and the Fall of</hi> Babylon <hi>and Antichriſt, whom the Lord would conſume and deſtroy by the Brightneſs of his coming, and</hi> Babylon <hi>ſhould never riſe no more at all, the great City of Confuſion; and the Holy City New</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhould come down like a Bride adorned for her Husband, which ſhould have no need of the elementary Lights, but the Glory of God and the Lamb is the Light thereof: if ye have Ears to hear, hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now is <hi>Babylon</hi> fired at both ends, <hi>and the Archers are come up againſt her out of the North Country,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaw, <hi>that ſhould make her deſolate,</hi> chap. 50. whoſe Bow is bent by the Strength of God, and ſhe muſt fall; for ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth her: Rocks nor Mountains can't hide her from the Wrath of the Lamb, flee whither ſhe can, from the Stroke of the Almighty's holy Life, that is come forth conquering and to conquer, like a Man of War, to plead with all fleſh by <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> who is King of kings and Lord of lords, whom the Armies in Heaven follow (whoſe Name is call'd, <hi>the Word of God, Him by whom the World was made</hi>) who hath taught their Hands to War, and Fingers to Fight in this Battle of the <hi>great God</hi> againſt <hi>Principalities and Powers, and Spiritual Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in high Places; whoſe Weapons are not Carnal, but Spiritual, and mighty through God, to the pulling down of the Strong Holds of Satan, the old Serpent, who is King of</hi> Babylon.</p>
            <p>Therefore flee out of her for your Lives <hi>(as Lot out of Sodom)</hi> for Fire is come down from God, that will conſume her; and he will bring forth his <hi>Glorious Work,</hi> his <hi>New Creation,</hi> which hath been long determin'd, and none ſhall hinder it; the <hi>Gates of Hell</hi> ſhall not prevail againſt his VVork, now begun in the Earth: <hi>the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100607:6"/>
               <p>ANd now a few words to you (in particular) that cry out againſt the Grace of God, which hath appeared to all men, <hi>as Inſufficient for Salvation;</hi> and yet profeſs the Scriptures to be your Rule, that teſtifieth of the Sufficiency of it; as the Lord God ſaid to his Servant <hi>Paul</hi> (in his Trouble and Affliction) <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> 2 Cor, 12.9. <hi>And by Grace are we ſaved, not of our ſelves, it is the Gift of God,</hi> Eph. 2.8. and God called it his Strength, <hi>My Strength is made perfect in Weakneſs:</hi> Now where did <hi>Paul,</hi> or any other of the Saints in Light, leave a Teſtimony behind them of its Inſufficiency, Inability or Weakneſs, whoſe words you (that have thus cryed) profeſs to be your Rule?</p>
               <p>Shew me your Rule for this; except from the Lyar from the beginning, which is your exact Parallel: For God ſaid to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and his Wife <hi>(If ye eat of the Tree of Knowledge) ye ſhall ſurely dye;</hi> The Serpent ſaid (in contradiction) <hi>Ye ſhall not ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye:</hi> God ſaid to <hi>Paul, My Grace is ſufficient;</hi> but you have ſaid, <hi>It is not ſufficient;</hi> like your Father, whoſe work ye do (notwithſtanding your Profeſſion) God calls it, <hi>His Strength;</hi> you ſay, <hi>Its Weakneſs, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nable:</hi> The Apoſtle (that proved it, and knew its effectual Work) ſaid, <hi>It brings Salvation; and the engrafted Word was able to ſave their Souls; and they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Word of his Grace: which was able to build them up,</hi> [Mark] <hi>and to give them an Inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi> Acts 20.32. here ye may read of its Ability. And the Spirit of Grace and Supplication was propheſied of, to be poured forth; and <hi>its the Spirit giveth Life</hi> (as Chriſt Jeſus ſaid) <hi>the Fleſh proſits nothing.</hi> So conſider theſe things, and ſee if ye be not in the Oppoſing and Gainſaying God, Chriſt Jeſus, and his. Apoſtles, like <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> reſiſting the Truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. And let God's Witneſs in you anſwer, and let all people judge.</p>
               <p>And was not the Fulneſs which was in Jeſus Chriſt (and the Glory <hi>John</hi> beheld in him) <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Truth?</hi> And is not <hi>Grace</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100607:6"/>and <hi>Truth</hi> one? Were not they ſaved by Grace? and did not the Truth make them free, who received it with Meekneſs, in the love of it? Doth not the Scripture teſtifie theſe things, which you call your Rule? or are they falſe Witneſſes that gave them forth? conſider it well in the Fear of God, and in Coolneſs; for that is the beginning of true Wiſdom. And leave off Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and learn to ſpeak every one Truth to his Neighbour: and do not ſmite your Fellow-Servants (for we profeſs one God and Chriſt for Salvation) nor eat and drink with the drunken (as ye have) any more; but be ſober, and watch, leſt the Lord come upon you unawares, and cut you aſſunder, and give you your Portion with Lyars, Hypocrites, and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; for God is not mocked, what you ſow ſhall you reap: and this is in true Love to your ſouls.</p>
               <p>Is not the Grace, the Light and the Truth one? and is not the Power and Spirit of God one? and is not God Light? is not the Word, the Father and Son one? and is not Chriſt the Light, and the Truth, and the Life? and is not he the Door, and the Way to Everlaſting Reſt? is there any Inheritance among the ſanctified Ones, but by him, whoſe Name is called, <hi>the Word of God, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha and the Omega?</hi> And if there be a Thouſand Names, were they not all of one? was not the holy Thing (in <hi>Mary</hi>) called, <hi>The Son of God;</hi> and <hi>Immanuel, God with us;</hi> and <hi>Jeſus, for he ſhall ſave his People from their Sins?</hi> Are there not many Names given to the one Saviour? or are there any more Saviours of the immortal ſoul in this caſe, beſide this one, that can ſave his People from their ſins? ſeeing God <hi>(who is Light)</hi> has ſaid, <hi>Beſide me there is no Saviour; I know not any,</hi> Iſa. 43.11. &amp; 44.8. Now if you can find out another, beſide him (who is the Word (in the beginning) you are wiſer then the old Serpent made <hi>Adam,</hi> when he beguiled them; or elſe you are Fools, and blind in your Imaginations.</p>
               <p>Therefore come to the true Tryal; the Light will make you (and your Airy Minds, Dark Hearts and Vain Thoughts) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, if ye will but bring all to it; and teach you to ſpeak and do Truth, and to ſtand in Awe, and be ſtill, that he may go before you, and lead you, in whom there is no occaſion of ſtumbling; this was the Saints Walking-place, and this Grace of God was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100607:7"/>their Teacher, wherein they witneſſed the Blood of Cleanſing, as ye may read.</p>
               <p>And this Grace of God hath appeared to all men, and its the Gift and Talent which he hath given (according to meaſure) to every one to profit withal; of which he will require an Account, how it hath been improved to his Glory, your Neighbours Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and your own Souls Comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For this is the Condemnation of the World, that Light is come into the World, and men loved Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe their deeds were Evil:</hi> The Condemnation is not, becauſe ye had not a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; but becauſe it is not improved, but hid, or buried in the Earth: For the Free Gift is come upon all, <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> through one; <hi>Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt, who lighteth every man that cometh into the World;</hi> this is Glad-tidings, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel preached to every Creature. Therefore deceive not your ſelves with Lying Vanities, neither feed on Husks, and that which dyes of it ſelf; but remember the Strait Gate and Narrow Way that leads in the Regeneration, in the Daily Croſs, to Life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal: For your great Notions, and Talk of Religion, Church and Worſhip, will not ſave you, nor give you an Inheritance with the Saints in Light, while you love Darkneſs, and live in it; if ye had all the words of holy Men from the beginning to this day, and of what Chriſt did and ſuffered, this is all but cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> while the Heart is far off, and the True God, and his Worſhip (in Spirit and in Truth) is not known by you; <hi>For ſuch the Father is now ſeeking to worſhip him, who worſhip him in the Spirit, and have no Confidence in the Fleſh:</hi> As a Shepherd ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out his Sheep in the day when they are ſcattered abroad, and gathering from the Mouthes of the Idol-Shepherds, and from off all the Barren Mountains, into the freſh Paſtures of Life and Peace, unto the Fold of Everlaſting Reſt, where no Ravenous Beaſt can come; Glory to the Lord God for evermore: And againſt this his Work (now begun) <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magogg</hi> ſhall never prevail.</p>
               <p>The Great Day of the Feaſt is come, wherein he is inviting the Poor in Spirit, the Hungry and Thirſty Souls; the Year of his Redeemed is come, and the Day of Vengeance is in his Heart;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100607:7"/>which Day the Apoſtle ſaw, and wrote of, that ſhould come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apoſtacy (or falling away) where the Man of Sin ſhould be conſumed, and deſtroyed; and the Great and Glorious Work of Reſtauration (determined) ſhould be accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>And this is from the Lord God Almighty, to all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth, whether they will hear or forbear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I have a few words more to all you that Sleight and make a Mock at the <hi>Light Within;</hi> as a Fooliſh, Erronious and Contemptable Thing.</head>
               <p>O Ye brutiſh among men! and Fools that hate Knowledge, and ignorant of the Scriptures of Truth, of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, which teſtifie of the True Light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the World; of which <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote, and <hi>John</hi> bore witneſs, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. though you profeſs their words: And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw Chriſt's Day, the True Light; did he ſee it Within, or Without? Anſwer me: And <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God before the Scriptures were given forth: And <hi>John</hi>'s Meſſage was, <hi>That God is Light:</hi> And God ſaid (of his People) <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them;</hi> is not this the Light VVithin, or is God changed? Did not <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſay, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.) <hi>The Lord was an Everlaſting Light; and in the Lord</hi> Jehovah <hi>was Everlaſting Strength; and bid people truſt in him; and that he had wrought all their Works [in] them?</hi> And did not the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſay, <hi>It is God that worketh in you, both to will and to do of his own good Pleaſure?</hi> And do you not make a Mock at God and Chriſt (that dwelleth in his People) and at the Scriptures, you that mock at the Light VVithin? Did not the Light that ſhined in the Saints, give them the true Knowledge of the only true God, and his Glory in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt? or did ever any know the true God, and Jeſus Chriſt (which is Life Eternal) by a Light VVithout? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The things of God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100607:8"/>knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God</hi> (by which they are revealed) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. <hi>And no man knows the Father, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him,</hi> Mat. 11.27. <hi>And the Inſpiration of the Almighty giveth man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> Job 32.8. Whether this Spirit. Inſpiration and Revelation be Within or Without? And by what did <hi>Abel, Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> (and many others) know God, before the Scriptures were given forth? or whether the Inviſible God (which is a Spirit) was ever ſeen by any carnal or viſible Eye; ſeeing <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaw no Similitude, but only heard a Voice? <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.12, 15, 16.</p>
               <p>May I not ſay to ſuch, <hi>Go to the Beaſts, and they ſhall teach thee; and to the Fowls, and they ſhall inſtruct thee?</hi> Hath not God (in his Univerſal Love and Tender Care) ordained a Univerſal Light, and Sun, to ſhine without, for the Well-being, Comfort and Refreſhment of all Creatures (Man and Beaſt) even of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bodies, throughout the Habitable Parts of the Earth? who cauſeth his Sun to ſhine, and Rain to fall on the Juſt and Unjuſt.</p>
               <p>And hath he not afforded or ordained a Univerſal Light and Son of Righteouſneſs for the Immortal Soul, the Inner Man, for its Help, Comfort and Refreſhment; which is of far greater value (in his ſight) then the Mortal Creatures? If he be thus ſtraightened, and his Arm and Hand of Love thus ſhortened; when came this to paſs? ſeeing his People and Children have found him (in all Ages) Unchangable, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and forever; who taught his Followers, <hi>To be Merciful, as their Heavenly Father is Merciful; who would have all men come to the Knowledge of the Truth, and be ſaved,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4.</p>
               <p>O the Blindneſs that is happened to people profeſſing <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> to deſpiſe and deride ſo Glorious a Comforter! It is no leſs then the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of Truth, which guides and leads its Children into all Truth, and ſhews them things to come. My ſoul pitties you, and I could even mourn in ſecret for you, knowing how miſerable your Feet will ſtumble at the dark Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains (who hate the Light) and the Mockers Bands be made ſtrong, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.22.</p>
               <p>I will ask you this Queſtion, and let the whole World anſwer me, if they can; <hi>What will become of the Immortal Part</hi> (or Inner
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100607:8"/>Man) <hi>which muſt have a Beeing forever, when the Body or Outward Man is periſhed? what will be its ſtate, when deprived of all viſible</hi> (or outward) <hi>Light to all eternity, and the Light Within wholy reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? and whether that ſtate be not the utter Darkneſs ſpoken of</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>where neither any Glory nor Benefit can be ſeen</hi> (but Torment) <hi>from the Light Within?</hi> Conſider it well in the Fear of God, and what will be thy Portion when the Deſire, Beauty and Comforts of thine outward Eyes are gone, and thou gone to thy long Home, if thou haſt no Benefit of the Light Within to comfort thee. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Eyes that ſee, and the Heart that underſtands and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves in the Light; for ſuch become the Children of Light (as Chriſt ſaid) and they are the Children of God: <hi>For God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 John 1.5.</p>
               <p>Objection, But ſome may object, and ſay, <hi>How can any be in utter Darkneſs, ſeeing thou affirmeſt, every one in the World is lighted with the true Light of Chriſt Jeſus; and that it is the Talent or Gift, given to every man to profit withal; and that all muſt give an Account of the Improvement of it? And how is it ſaid to be taken from a man, and he caſt into utter Darkneſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is thus taken away, Through Diſobedience to it (the not improving of it) the Benefit and Comfort of it is loſt; and if a man live and dye in the ſtate of Rebellion, it only remaineth in him as a Tormenting Worm, that never dyes; And thus you may read of the Wicked and Slothful Servant, who had a Talent, and did not improve it, as required, but hid it in the Earth (read within) this was his Condemnation; and this is the Fire that never goes out. And the Rich Man in Hell Torment (who had lived in the fulneſs of Pleaſures) had enough to ſee himſelf in Darkneſs, and Tormented in the Flame; and <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in Joy and Comfort, which added to his Miſery, and not to his Refreſhment; for he deſired but a little of their Water, and could not get it, as ye may ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23, 24, 25, 26.</p>
               <p>And it was ſaid of them that ſeparated themſelves from the Saints in Light, <hi>That they were ſenſual, having not the Spirit:</hi> that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100607:9"/>is, They (not being guided, lead and taught by it, but were diſobrdient to it) had not the Benefit and Comfort of it, nor a right Underſtanding by it of the Way of God, nor true Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Work and Myſteries of God, which were the things that belong to their Everlaſting Peace; but it reprov'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd them for their Rebellion, as it is written, <hi>The Rebellious dwell in a Dry Land,</hi> Pſal. 68.6.</p>
               <p>But the Apoſtles and Servants of God, who were led by it, had the comfort of it, and it abode with them ſo forever; <hi>and they handled, taſted and felt the Word of Life, which was in the beginning, and they fed upon it, and it nouriſh'd and ſtrengthen'd them with all Might in the Inter-Man; and it was a Sword and Armour to them, a Defence againſt Evil and Darkneſs:</hi> And others, they caſt it behind their backs, and ſo muſt needs go in Darkneſs; <hi>For the Word is a Light so their Feet that take heed to it, and it is powerful;</hi> ſo people caſt that which is powerful behind them, and then complain, <hi>they have no Power;</hi> this is the ſtate of the Diſobedient: <hi>But to as many as recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, to them he gave Power (even to as many as believe in his Name) to become the Sons of God; and he is the Author of eternal Salvation to as many as obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9.</p>
               <p>And ſo <hi>Diſobedience</hi> is the Ground of man's Ruin and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not the Inſufficiency of God's Gifts, or any ſtraitneſs in him towards Mankind.</p>
               <p>So remember you are warned, and its the Day of your Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Lord God, in Love to your Immortal Souls; and prize your Inch of precious time, and fear God, and give Glory to him; and worſhip him that made Heaven, and Earth, and the Fountain of Water; for the Hour of his Judgments is come (in which <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt fall) and his inviſible Glory be revealed more and more, to the Ends of the Earth, till the kingdoms of this world become the Lord's, and he ſhall Raign forever and ever, world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent of this World, and revealed them to Babes; for ſo it pleaſeth thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100607:9"/>
               <head>A few words (in true Breathings of Love) unto you that are turned (in this Day of his Power) from Darkneſs to the Light, and do believe in it, and have taſted that the Lord is Gracious.</head>
               <p>DEar Friends, dwell in it, dwell low, and cool, and ſtill, in the true Dread of the Lord (Wiſdom's Gate and Door) and there keep your Watch, and be ſober; for your Enemy ſeeks to devour you; all Opertunities he waits for his Prey, to catch and deſtroy your poor tender Souls, who are eſcaping from him, whoſe deſires are after God, and things Above: Remember it is the <hi>Old Serpent,</hi> and he wants neither Age nor Cunning, he is ſtill more ſubtil then any Beaſt, and is Curſed forever: You have no Armour againſt him like the Armour of Light; therefore keep it on (and Watch and Pray) continually; and wreſtle againſt this Principality and Power of Darkneſs, the Enemy of Mankind, which lies near to many; and then he cannot enter, he cannot ſpoil you, nor ſow his Tares of Corruption and Wickedneſs; but while men ſleep he ſows them, that was his firſt Oportunity, while men ſlept, and hath alwayes been, and is the ſame now, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So dear Friends, keep your Watch, its the Word of the Lord to you; then you keep out the Enemy, and over him, in true Dominion and Peace; and your Soul is Comforted, and God Glorified, and his Work proſpers in the Earth, which prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, who hath Wonderfully and Graciouſly Appeared in this his Day for the deliverance of his Choſen; and he will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more and more, till <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is made the Praiſe of the whoſe Earth, and none ſhall hinder.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100607:10"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to thoſe Cries among ſome ignorant People, <hi>viz.</hi> Where did you ever hear or read in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of a people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of a Light Within people, as you <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> do? And is not your Religion a New Religion, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Twenty Years ſtanding, not heard of before? And whether you, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> do not deny the Scriptures to be the Word of God? And whether you do not hold that dangerous Tenet of Perfection in this Life?</head>
            <head type="sub">Given forth for the ſake of the Simple Inquirer, and to ſilence the Ignorance of Fooliſh Men, and to Reprove the Scorner, who Err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God.</head>
            <p>AS for our Religion, it is no New Religion, neither is it onely of a late ſtanding (as you ſuppoſe) and yet as new to many now, as Chriſt's was unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> who did not believe his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>For the Light is a New and a Strange Thing to ſuch as were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100607:10"/>born Blind, and have alwayes lived in Darkneſs, though it hath been the ſtanding Rule and Path of the Juſt from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as you may read and ſee (if you are not ſtill blind) in what followeth.</p>
            <p>Though the Name <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKER</hi> hath been given us in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and Scorn, by Scoffers and Mockers (which the Apoſtle ſaid would be in the laſt dayes) yet we know that the Holy Men, and Servants of God of old, did witneſs <hi>Quaking</hi> and <hi>Trembling,</hi> who would have been mocked by you, had they been in your dayes, who were <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Tremblers,</hi> and preached the <hi>Light</hi> above Twenty Hundred Years ago, as ye may read in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth, from the Mouthes of more then two or three Witneſſes, herein mention'd, which is but in ſhort of what may be declared.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes,</hi> a Servant of God, by whoſe hand the Lord wrought Mighty Wonders, and deliver'd his People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Land of Darkneſs; he was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and a <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler;</hi> and all the people of the Camp <hi>Trembled, Exod.</hi> 19.16. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that Trembled at the Words and Commandment of God were the Choice Men, and Chief in Counſel with <hi>Ezra;</hi> and in the Work of the Lord, in building the Temple, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.4. and 10.3. (ſee whom the Lord chuſeth to do his Work.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> a Prophet and Servant of God, who did and wrought great Things in his day, was a <hi>Quaker</hi> and <hi>Trembler</hi> chap. 12. verſ. 18.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And <hi>Iſaac</hi> Trembled very exceedingly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.33. Would not you (like <hi>Iſhmael</hi>) have Mocked ſuch an exceeding <hi>Trembler,</hi> and called him <hi>Quaker,</hi> had he been in your dayes? Conſider it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Job.</hi> a Servant of God, who ſaw God, and knew his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100607:11"/>Redeemer live, in his day, an Upright man, Trembled, <hi>Job</hi> 21.6. &amp; 19.25.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And <hi>Daniel,</hi> a Man greatly beloved of God (in whom was an Excellent Spirit of Light and Underſtanding) he was a <hi>Trembler,</hi> and the men with him <hi>Quaked;</hi> and we do not read the <hi>Heathens</hi> Mocked them, chap. 10. nor called them <hi>Quakers.</hi> And King <hi>Darius</hi> made a Decree, <hi>That all men</hi> Fear <hi>and</hi> Tremble <hi>before the God of</hi> Daniel, chap. 6.26.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And <hi>David,</hi> a Man after God's own Heart, was a <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler,</hi> who did great things for God and his People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.5.119.120. but he was the Song of the Drunkards, and deſpiſed of (<hi>Saul</hi>'s Daughter) his Wife.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Habakkuk <hi>Trembled, Prophets of the Lord all owned Trembling.</hi> Hab. 3.16.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Jeremiah <hi>Trembled, Prophets of the Lord all owned Trembling.</hi> Jer. 5.22. &amp;. 23.9.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Joel <hi>and Trembled, Prophets of the Lord all owned Trembling.</hi> Joel. 2.1.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Amos <hi>Trembled, Prophets of the Lord all owned Trembling.</hi> Amos 8.8.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Nahum,</hi> a Prophet of God, witneſſed the Mountains to Quake at his Preſence, chap. 1.5.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (who ſpoke in the Name of God) ſaid, <hi>Hear the Word of the Lord, all ye that</hi> Tremble <hi>at his Word; your Brethren that hated you, and that caſt you out for my Name ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be Glorified; but he ſhall appear to your Joy, and they ſhall be Aſhamed,</hi> chap. 66. Hear this, ye Outſide-Lip-Profeſſors and Scoffers.</p>
            <p>And ſaith God, <hi>To this man will I look, even to him that is Poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and</hi> Trembleth <hi>at my Word,</hi> chap. 66.1.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul,</hi> an Apoſtle and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Trembled;</hi> and the Converted Goaler <hi>Trembled;</hi> and <hi>Felix Trembled,</hi> reaſoning with <hi>Paul</hi> about Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6, 24, 25. &amp; 16.29. Would not you Unrighteous and Untemperate Ones have ſcoffed at them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100607:11"/>and called them <hi>Quakers?</hi> Conſider it, and Repent, and Dread the Lord God, who will not be mocked.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> preached in much Trembling, and in the Power and Demonſtration of the Spirit of God; and his Work was, To turn people from Darkneſs to the Light: and ſaid, <hi>God</hi> (who is Light) <hi>had ſhined into their Hearts; And the true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were to work out their Salvation with Fear and Trembling; And it was God that workt in them, &amp;c.</hi> as you may read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.3, 4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. And many more <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> and <hi>Tremblers</hi> preached the Light, the ſame true Light which <hi>John</hi> bore teſtimony of, that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw the Day of Chriſt (the true Light) before <hi>Moſes</hi> was born, who wrote of Chriſt, and the Law of God; and <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God before <hi>Abraham</hi> was born, who was the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> and had the Witneſs in himſelf, <hi>That he pleaſed God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Preached and Propheſied of the Light; and the Houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> (when Idolatrous) was called to walk in the Light of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. &amp; 60. &amp; 2.5. And Chriſt was further promiſed to be for a Covenant of Light and Salvation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.17. &amp; 51 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks of the Voice and Glory of God, when he had ſeen the Fire and Lightening, chap. 1. But this is hid from your Eyes who are in the Dark.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> declared of the Light, chap. 2.22. &amp; 5.11, 12. And the Queen (of that Country) ſaid, <hi>It was [in] him; and that it was an Excellent Spirit:</hi> and did not Mock him, nor at the Light Within; as many do who profeſs <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but are worſe then the <hi>Heathens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> preached the Light Within, and VVord VVithin, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 27.1. &amp; 36.9. &amp; 97.11. &amp; 37.6. &amp; 119.11. &amp; verſ. 105.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Job</hi> owned and preached the Light, chap. 24 16. &amp; 25 3. &amp; 33.28. And he ſaw God with his Eye, which is Light, chap. 42.5.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> preached the Light VVithin, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100607:12"/>
            <p> And Chriſt Jeſus preached the Light, and bid People <hi>believe in it</hi> (and ſo do we) <hi>that they might become the Children of the Light,</hi> John 12.35, 36.</p>
            <p>And <hi>John,</hi> his Meſſage was, <hi>That God is Light,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>And God ſaid, <hi>He would dwell [in] his People,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. And <hi>the Saints Inheritance is in the Light,</hi> Col. 1.12. And <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality dwelleth in the Light,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.16. which is the Saints Inheritance, though the Unſanctified, Dark and Unclean have no part in it (in that ſtate) or Knowledge of the Wayes of it, while they Rebel againſt it, as you may read <hi>Job</hi> 24.13.</p>
            <p>Much more might be written, as to this particular; but this is onely mentioned (in ſhort) for the ſake of ſuch as may ſimply inquire, and to ſtop the Mouth of the Lyar and Scoffer, who ſpeak evil of thoſe things they underſtand not.</p>
            <p>And alſo, I do affirm, That the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Tremblers,</hi> which were Servants of God of old (as I have here ſhewed) did bare a Teſtimony againſt all the Unrighteouſneſs of men (in their day) without Reſpect of Perſons, in Plain Language to the people (and did preach the Light) as we have done, and yet do (in our Age.) And the Goſpel of this Kingdom (of God Within) muſt be preached for a Witneſs unto all Nations, and then ſhall the End come.</p>
            <p>They teſtified againſt Idolatry; againſt the Proud, Mockers and Scoffers, againſt the Rebellious, who rebelled againſt the Light; and pronouced many Woes againſt the Hypocrites, and Falſe Shepherds, and Hirelings, ſuch as ſeek't their Gain from their Quarter, that fed themſelves, and bore Rule by their Means; and Propheſied for Money, and Barley, and Pieces of Bread; that ruled with Force and Cruelty, puſhing with their Horns, like as ſome bruit Beaſts have done in this Age; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the Lord God did move many of his Servants to teſtifie, as may be yet remembred. And there was a time when Chriſt Jeſus was daily ſtriving with ſuch in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to have gathered them in their day, but they refuſed; and then after ſaid, <hi>They are Blind Leaders of the Blind, let them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100607:12"/>alone;</hi> which was an Expreſſion of a ſad Sin and Conſequence; for they would both fall into the Ditch. Which may ſerve for an Anſwer to ſome that have inquired, <hi>Why we do not viſit them as formerly;</hi> if they had Eyes to diſcern the Times and Seaſons, which are in the Father's Hand. Much might be ſaid to this.</p>
            <p>They teſtified againſt the Bloody, againſt Robbers, and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and againſt the Covetous, Violent, and Oppreſſors of the people. And <hi>Zephaniah</hi> cryed, <hi>Wo to the Filthy and Poluted Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing City, whoſe Princes were Roaring Lyons, and Judges Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves, and Prophets light and treacherous,</hi> chap. 3. And read <hi>Amos</hi> 6. And againſt ſuch as were in <hi>Cain</hi>'s Way, and <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Way,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Michah</hi> 3. <hi>Nahum</hi> 3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> chap. 34. <hi>Jer.</hi> chap. 4. Iſa. 10.1. and Chap. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 11. And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> pronounced, <hi>Wo to the Crown of Pride, to the Drunkards of</hi> Ephraim; <hi>they ſhall be troden under Feet,</hi> Iſa. chap. 28. <hi>And Wo unto them that decree <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous Decrees, &amp;c.</hi> chap. 10.1. <hi>and to the Rebellious Children, that took Counſel, but not of the Lord; and that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with a Covering, and not of his Spirit; that they might add ſin to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear this all ye Outſide-Profeſſors of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt the Light and Counſel of the Lord, and his Spirit Within, which reproves you for your Sin and Hypocriſie; your Covering is too narrow, and your Bed too ſhort, to hide you from the Wrath of the Lamb.</p>
            <p>The Sheep's Clothing will not ſerve you, while you are inwardly ravened from the Truth (required in the Inward parts) no more then <hi>Cain</hi>'s Sacrifice did, while Sin lay at his Door. The Day of the Lord is come that diſcovers you and your works, and the Fire ſhall try them.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt Jeſus cryed many Woes againſt the Scribes, and Phariſees, and Lawyers, and Blind Guides; and called them, <hi>Hypocrites, and Serpents, and Vipers.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> cryed, <hi>Wo to the Inhabitants of the Earth;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>The Devil is come down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you,</hi> Rev. 12.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100607:13"/>
            <p> And the Serpents, and Vipers, and <hi>Cain,</hi> and Blind Guides, (like Moles) are the Earth's Inhabiters; and the Roaring Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Evening Wolves, and them that puſht with their Horns, and the Swine, Dogs, and Foxes, and Thorns, and Thiſtles Chriſt ſpoke of, are all of the Earth's Inhabitants, and all the Ravenous and Unclean Beaſts; and the Devil went into the Swine; and <hi>Cain,</hi> the Wicked one, ſacrificed, and ſlew his Brother about it, a Vagabond and Fugative in the Earth, an Inhabitant there; and ſo the Wo remains upon all in his Way, and in <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Way (Blind-Guides Way) who could not ſee the Angel: And ſuch cannot ſee the VVay of the Lord, nor his People, nor their States and Conditions, nor their VVorſhip, till they are turned to the Light, and the Eye become opened, which the Godd of this VVorld hath blinded.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have no Pearls to caſt to Swine; but to this man hath God regard, <hi>That is Poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and Trembleth at his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherefore Fear God, and conſider theſe things, and be VViſe, and do not Mock at the LIGHT, nor at the QUAKERS; but remember your Latter-end, and Repent, leſt the Lord's Anger be kindled againſt you, and you periſh in your Folly: For the Holy Men of God prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the LIGHT, and witneſſed QUAKING and TREMBLING, as I have ſhewed you. So take VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning while you have time, and prize it.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>SCRIPT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES,</hi> we own them in their place, as Chriſt Jeſus ſaid of them, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. and as the Servants of God, in Ages paſt, acknowledged and teſtified, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. To be a Trus Declaration; and leave it to the VVitneſs of God in you all to conſider and judge, whether they are all the <hi>Word,</hi> or <hi>Words</hi> of God, yea or nay, as by what followeth,</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100607:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the Bible, or Scriptures, are many words relating to divers Matters, which we do not Queſtion the Truth of the Relation thereof.</p>
            <p>There are the words of God; and of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in the Fall; and of the Serpent, that beguiled them: I hope you will not ſay, Theſe are are all the VVord, or VVords of God; but very much to be diſtinguiſhed, by them that have a Right Underſtanding, as Contradictory.</p>
            <p>And there are the Words of <hi>Cain</hi> (to God) who ſlew his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Brother about Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>And the words of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job;</hi> Holy Men. And there are alſo the Words of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the Prophane Perſon; and the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and <hi>Sodomites;</hi> and of them that cauſed <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> to be Caſt into the Lyon's Den, for Praying to his God.</p>
            <p>And the Words of <hi>David, Mordecai</hi> and <hi>Eſther.</hi> And of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> that Fought againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and of Proud Wicked <hi>Hamon,</hi> who ſought the <hi>Jews</hi> Deſtruction, becauſe <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> would not do him Reverence.</p>
            <p>And the Words of <hi>Ahah</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> that Murdered <hi>Naboth</hi> for his Vineyard; and the Words of <hi>Samuel</hi> to him, whom he called his Enemy, though a Holy Man.</p>
            <p>And there are the Words of <hi>Saul</hi> (who ſought <hi>David</hi> to ſlay him) and of the Witch he went to; and of the Prieſt's Son <hi>Paſhur,</hi> Chief Governour, &amp;c. who ſmote <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> Are all theſe the Words of God?</p>
            <p>And there are the Words of the Devil concerning <hi>Job,</hi> who would have deſtroyed him; but confeſſed, <hi>God had made a Hedge about him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a Relation of the Reign of Good Kings, and alſo of many Bad Ones. And of the Falſe Prophets and Hirelings, that ſeek't for their Gain from their Quarter, and ſpoke Lyes to the People, whom God never ſent, and ſo did not profit them at all who heard and believed them.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100607:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> And in the Scriptures are recorded the Words and Sayings, Works and Sufferings of Chriſt Jeſus (the true Prophet, of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote) and the Words of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that Tempted him; and of <hi>Judas,</hi> that Betrayed him; and of the Prieſts, that gave Large Money to the Souldiers, to tell Lyes, How his Diſciples had ſtole him away while they were Aſleep. Is that likely, They could tell what was become of Him, being all Aſleep? VVhat a Shift, and poor Refuge of Lyes, the Devil putteth his Servants to, when his Kingdom is going down?</p>
            <p>And there are the words of <hi>Pilate,</hi> that delivered him into their hands, and Waſhed his own (but that would not do) and of them that Blindfolded and Mocked him.</p>
            <p>And there are the Words of the Holy Apoſtles, and their ſeveral Letters and Epiſtles to the ſeveral Congregations of the Lord's People. And alſo, of the Vagabond <hi>Jews,</hi> who bound themſelves under a Curſe, Neither to Eat nor Drink till they had Killed <hi>Paul.</hi> And of the Captain that Reſcued him out of their hands. And the words of the Orator, that called him, A Peſtilent Fellow. And of them that ſaid, Chriſt had a Devil, and caſt out Devils by <hi>Belzebub.</hi> Are theſe all the Words of God? Much leſs the VVORD, that was in the Beginning, that Liveth and Abideth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>And in the Scriptures may be read the Words of the Perſecutors, who ſtrictly Charged the Apoſtles. To leave Preaching in the Name of Jeſus (the True Light and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God) But <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> Sung in the Priſon; and they could not but ſpeak that which they had Seen and Heard of Chriſt Jeſus; and could not Flee, like the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that leave the Sheep when the Wolf comes among them: For a Work of Neceſſity was required of them, to turn the People from Darkneſs to the Light, from Satans Power to the Power of God: And they had the Word of Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. And this Word was in the Beginning, by whom all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100607:14"/>things were made, before the Scriptures were; of which the Scriptures teſtifie, <hi>John</hi> 1. and they are a True De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. And this is our Belief concerning them.</p>
            <p>And ſo we make a true Diſtinction between the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and the Thing or Things reported of, <hi>as Iſaiah</hi> did, who ſaid, <hi>Who hath believed our Report? and to whom is the Arm of the Lord Revealed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Record which God gave of his Son, is not the Son himſelf; but to be Believed concerning Him.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Scriptures are not the Word; for that is Chriſt's Name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.13. <hi>John</hi> 1.1. Nor can they all truly and properly be called, <hi>The Words ef God,</hi> as I have here demonſtrated (in ſhort) to the View of all who are not wilfully Blind.</p>
            <p>So come to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which ſhines in your Dark Hearts; in which you may ſee your ſelves, and your Ignorance, and Vain Thoughts, and Hard Speeches; and learn to put a Difference between the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and the Vile in your own Particulars, and then you will divide aright between Good Men and Wicked Men, and their Words and Actions, as between Light and Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>And as for our holding that Dangerous Tenet (as you call it) of <hi>Perfection in this Life;</hi> I Anſwer,</p>
            <p>We hold no other Perfection, or Tenet, then what the Holy Men of God of old did; who did hold the Head, Chriſt Jeſus, and laid hold of Eternal Life; in which is no Danger, or Imperfection, but ſafety and Peace; who is come to Deſtroy the Devil, and his Works, which hath made people Imperfect, and brought them into Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the Pit of Darkneſs and Ignorance, by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100607:15"/>in which lieth the Danger of Everlaſting Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in this Broad Way: but in Chriſt, the Truth, the Life, the Way to the Father, is no Imperfection or Danger, as I have ſaid, but Eternal Life and Salvation; in which Life we have Perfect Peace, as our Minds are ſtaid on him, and not in any other. And he bids his People, <hi>Be Perfect, as their Heavenly Father is Perfect.</hi> And this is no Dangerous Tenet, To obey God and Chriſt Jeſus; which you your ſelves have promiſed, and do not perform, but are Diſobedient; and here lies your Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, In profeſſing God and Chriſt in Words, but in Works deny him, and are Ignorant of him.</p>
            <p>For, No other Perfection, or Dangerous Tenet, do we hold at this day, then what we were bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and walk in when we were Children, and to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs performed by the Spirit and Grace of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us. And in the ſame Covenant are you ingaged, and have promiſed to fulfil it on your part, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> Therefore look you to the Danger of breaking your Promiſe made to God, as ye may Read in the Publick <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> (and conſider it well) in which we were taught by our (then) Teachers, (as people are now)</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>To renounce the Devil, and all his Works; the Pomps and Vanities of this Wicked World, and all the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts of the Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>And to believe all the Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>To keep God's Holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to Walk in the ſame all the Dayes of our Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did we and you Ingage and Promiſe unto God; which is a ſtate of as great Perfection as can be witneſſed, and is to be performed and fulfilled in all true <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100607:15"/>
            <p> Therefore weigh the Matter well, and ſee where lieth the Danger; on them that wait upon God, to receive his holy Spirit and Grace, to perform what hath been promiſed; or on them that promiſe, and do not regard to perform their Vows to God, as you and your Teachers have done? who have Reproached us for the ſame things which you your ſelves profeſs to God in words, like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> of old, who ſaid, <hi>God was their Father,</hi> and yet put Chriſt Jeſus to Death, becauſe he acknowledged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>the Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the Lord judge between us and you, and open your Eyes, that you may ſee a Difference between him that Sweareth, and him that feareth an Oath; between him that doth in Deed and Truth ſerve God, and him that ſerveth him not, but onely with the Lips, and the Heart far off, which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth; who is onely Worſhipped in the Spirit and in the Truth (which is Perfect) And then you will perceive, That our Religion, and Worſhip, and what we hold, is neither New, Strange, or Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as ye have imagined; but the Good Old Way of Holineſs, the Pure Religion, and true Spiritual Worſhip, which God alone (who is Perfect) hath ſet up, and is Well-pleaſed with, who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it: And this was before the Devil's Works were (which hath made People Blind, and Miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Imperfect by Tranſgreſſion.) The Holy, Pure and Perfect Life, and its Works was the Firſt, and will be the Laſt upon the Earth, the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the Enemy of Mankind that ſowed the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100607:16"/>Tares; the Lord ſowed Good Seed in the Field, the Wicked One ſowed the Bad, whoſe Work the Son of God is manifeſted to deſtroy; and he will O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn again and again, till he comes to Reign, whoſe Right it is. And againſt this his Work (now begun) the Gates of Hell and Death ſhall not prevail, <hi>the Mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more might be declared, as to this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but thus much (in ſhort) I have given, in Anſwer to theſe things, that your Eyes might be opened, who Err in Viſion, and Stumble in Judgment; that the things belonging to your Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Peace might not be hid from you, in this your Day.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So Fear God, and prize your Precious Time; this is in true Love to all your Souls, by a Friend to all People,</hi> William Bayly.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
